Guide to the Rice University Athletic Committee records, 1959-1991 UA 113
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Athletic Committee records
1959-1991
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University. Athletics Committee.
UA 113
1 Linear Feet (7 boxes) 5 are unprocessed at LSC
Meeting minutes and correspondence of the Rice University Athletic Committee, 1959-1991.
Biographical / Historical
The current day Athletics Committee was originally organized in 1916 as the Committee on Outdoor Sports, with William Ward Watkin as its chairman. In 1971, its name was changed to the Committee on Intercollegiate Athletics, and in 1977 the committee was reorganized and renamed the Rice University Athletic Committee (RUAC).
Mission of the RUAC as of 2001: Acting in an advisory capacity to the President, the Rice University Athletics Committee (hereafter called the RUAC) shall have general cognizance of all extramural athletic programs of the University. In performing this function, the Committee activities include the following responsibilities: 1. Formulate recommendations for internal and external policy necessary for the proper conduct of all University athletic activities. This includes continuing review of intercollegiate sports to insure full compliance with laws and regulations of any regional or national governing bodies in which the University holds membership.
1. Formulate recommendations for internal and external policy necessary for the proper conduct of all University athletic activities. This includes continuing review of intercollegiate sports to insure full compliance with laws and regulations of any regional or national governing bodies in which the University holds membership.
2. Specifically the Committee will include the following in its duties in regard to all intercollegiate activity: a. Review the general intercollegiate sport budgets, transmitting its recommendations to the President annually. B: When practical, make recommendations through its chairman concerning the Athletic Director and all athletic head coaching appointments. C: Provide recommendations and guidance in the formation of policies regarding the conduct of the Athletics program. A partial list of current policies in which committee oversight is required includes: i. Need-based financial aid; ii. Form and substance of communication with faculty council, in regard to such issues as graduation rates of student-athletes and academic admissions; iii. Responsibility for oversight audit of athletic eligibility; iv. Compliance with NCAA certification in regard to gender equity; v. Exit interviews of student-athletes; vi. oversight of any policy change by academic departments that may impact the athletic programs. D: Review the recommendations of the Athletic Director on the award of all varsity letters.
3. Make recommendations concerning the use of athletic facilities by on-campus or off-campus groups in conformity with University policy covering facility usage.
Membership: The Committee is composed of 16 voting members, appointed by the President. The Chairman and eight others who shall be faculty members are appointed as follows: Chairman for a three-year term, at the pleasure of the President Eight with 4 year staggered terms. Included among the faculty members will be the Faculty Athletics Representative.
Scope and Contents
Meeting minutes and correspondence of the Rice University Athletic Committee, 1959-1991.
Access Restrictions
Access to this material requires written permission from the President's Office. Please contact the Woodson Research Center for assistance in obtaining permission.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred from the Rice University President's Papers (Pitzer, Hackerman).
Related Material
For further information on athletics policy at Rice University, see the Rice University Board of Trustees minute books and the President's Office records for the relevant time period.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; College sports -- Management; College sports; Sports
Document Types
corrrespondence; minutes (administrative records)
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University. Athletics Committee.
- Series I: Minutes and correspondence, 1959-1974, 92785
  - 1959/60 - 1960/61, 92797 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1961/62 - 1962/63, 92796 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1963/64 - 1964/65, 92795 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1965/66, 92794 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1966/67, 92793 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - List of ticket holders, 1966/67, 92792 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1967/68, 92791 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1968/69 - 1969/70, 92790 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1970/71, 92789 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1971/72, 92788 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1972/73, 92787 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - 1973/74, 92786 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Minutes and correspondence, 1974-1991, 92772
  - 1974/75, 92784 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1975/76, 92783 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - 1976/77, 92782 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SWC proposed schedules (football), 1975-1980, 92781 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1977/78, 92780 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1978/79, 92779 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1979/80, 92778 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera, 92777 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1980/81, 92776 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1981/82 - 1982/83, 92775 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1984/85 - 1986/87, 92774 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1988, 1990-1991, 92773 (Box 2, Folder 13)